[
    {
        "course": "geography",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 1,
        "year": 1998,
        "question": "The vegetation belt associated with valuable hard wood is the",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 1,
        "options": [
            "Sahel Savanna",
            "Tropical rainforest",
            "Coniferous forest",
            "Mediterranean forest",
            "Moutane forest"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "geography",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 2,
        "year": 1998,
        "question": "Temperate grasslands are generally important for",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 2,
        "options": [
            "mining",
            "floating of logs",
            "animal grazing",
            "processing of meat and cheese",
            "burning of grass for fuel"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "geography",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 3,
        "year": 1998,
        "question": "The greatest problem in the use of solar energy is",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 1,
        "options": [
            "the high risk in its usage",
            "its unreliability from day to day and season to season",
            "the high intensity associatated with the sun",
            "the high cost of transporting it for domestic use",
            "its frequency of power failure"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "geography",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 4,
        "year": 1998,
        "question": "The sparse population in the Amazon Basin is best explained by the",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 2,
        "options": [
            "very high tmperature all the year round",
            "low range of temperature for agriculture",
            "thick vegetation for settlements and agriculture",
            "high relief and rugged terrain",
            "high humidity and moist conditions"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "geography",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 5,
        "year": 1998,
        "question": "One danger about the present rate of increase in world population is",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 4,
        "options": [
            "an improved standard of living",
            "the fear of submergence of the earth",
            "the high ratio of adults to children",
            "decline in the supply of labour",
            "an acute food shortage"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "geography",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 6,
        "year": 1998,
        "question": "A rapid population growth in a region can be caused by",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 3,
        "options": [
            "more deaths than births",
            "high emigration",
            "the use of family planning methods",
            "improved medical care",
            "natural hazards"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "geography",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 7,
        "year": 1998,
        "question": "Which of the following represents an urban-rural migration?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 2,
        "options": [
            "A student from the village school gains admission to the university in the town",
            "Moving to the urban centre for medical service",
            "Travelling from Lagos to the village on retirement",
            "A civil servant gets transfered from one town to another",
            "A parent from the village visits his son in the town"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "geography",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 8,
        "year": 1998,
        "question": "A rural settlement is a settlement classified by",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 3,
        "options": [
            "age",
            "site",
            "altitude",
            "function",
            "shape"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "geography",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 9,
        "year": 1998,
        "question": "Which of the following settlement types is strongly associated with tourism?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 3,
        "options": [
            "Rural settlement",
            "Commercial centre",
            "Port town",
            "Holiday resort",
            "Confluence town"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "geography",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 10,
        "year": 1998,
        "question": "Air transportation has a low patronage because it",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 4,
        "options": [
            "is fast",
            "is irregular",
            "is useful in war time only",
            "opens up remote areas",
            "is costly"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "geography",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 11,
        "year": 1998,
        "question": "All the following are light industries except",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 0,
        "options": [
            "ship building , locomotive and chemicals",
            "printing, flour-milling and furniture -making",
            "locomotives, electionics and texiles",
            "paper, furniture and electronics",
            "electronics furniture and ship -building"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "geography",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 12,
        "year": 1998,
        "question": "One major problem of development in the Niger-Benue trough is",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 4,
        "options": [
            "inadequate rainfall",
            "very high relief",
            "desert encroachment",
            "inadequate water supply",
            "excesive flooding"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "geography",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 13,
        "year": 1998,
        "question": "Which of the following modes of transportation in Nigeria is limited by weather?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 3,
        "options": [
            "water",
            "pipeline",
            "road",
            "air",
            "rail"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "geography",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 14,
        "year": 1998,
        "question": "Irrigation farming is highly practiced in Northern Nigeria because of the",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 2,
        "options": [
            "aboundant plains for the cultivation",
            "limited maret for its products",
            "inadequate rainfall and presence of many rivers",
            "good roads and aboundant capital",
            "skilled labour and love for vegetation"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "geography",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 15,
        "year": 1998,
        "question": "One important consequence of the location of Nigeria between latitudes 4<sup>0</sup>and 14<sup>0</sup>north of the Equator is that she",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 0,
        "options": [
            "enjoys a hot, wet, tropical climate",
            "has a luxuriant vegetation",
            "has the north easterly winds prevailling throughout the year",
            "receives rainfall throughout the year",
            "enjoys land and sea breeze"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "geography",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 16,
        "year": 1998,
        "question": "Which of the following is true of manufacturing industries in Nigeria?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 0,
        "options": [
            "Most of them produce consumer goods",
            "Large quantities of their products are exported",
            "They depend entirely on local raw materials",
            "They were established in pre-colonial times",
            "They are evenly distributed throughout the country"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "geography",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 17,
        "year": 1998,
        "question": "Trade among west African countries is less developed mainly because",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 0,
        "options": [
            "they were ruled by different colonial powers which created a barrier to communication",
            "the products of one country are basically similar to those of the others",
            "there are no international railway lines to transport the bulky items of trade across the borders",
            "of ethnic sentiments of people in one country against the other",
            "no west African country has surpluses of commodities to export to the other countries"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "geography",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 18,
        "year": 1998,
        "question": "The southern most latitude in Africa is approximately",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 2,
        "options": [
            "20<sup>0</sup>S",
            "30<sup>0</sup>S",
            "35<sup>0</sup>S",
            "40<sup>0</sup>S",
            "45<sup>0</sup>S"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "geography",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 19,
        "year": 1998,
        "question": "Which of the following does not explain the poor development of inland waterways in Africa?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 0,
        "options": [
            "Lack of goods to carry along the routes",
            "Presence of rapids and waterfalls",
            "Obstruction by floating vegetation",
            "High seasonality of the rivers",
            "Crossing of many political boundaries by the rivers"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "geography",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 20,
        "year": 1998,
        "question": "The savanna lands of East Africa are best known for their",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 0,
        "options": [
            "wildlife",
            "rich mineral resources",
            "inter-ethnic wars",
            "large rivers",
            "industries"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "geography",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 21,
        "year": 1998,
        "question": "The rampant famine in some parts of Africa is caused by all the following except",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 0,
        "options": [
            "Unstable prices paid to farmers for their products",
            "Unreliable rainfall",
            "Civil strife and unrest",
            "Ravage of corps by pests",
            "Infertile soil and soil erosion"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "geography",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 22,
        "year": 1998,
        "question": "Which of the following West Africa countries is the largest producer of groundnut?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 1,
        "options": [
            "Burkina Faso",
            "Mali",
            "Guinea Bissau",
            "Senegal",
            "Liberia"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "geography",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 23,
        "year": 1998,
        "question": "The figure 1 is a",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 1,
        "options": [
            "wind rose",
            "pie chart",
            "proportional circle",
            "divided proportional circle"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "geography",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 24,
        "year": 1998,
        "question": "The total value of the word's export commodities represented in Fig 1 is",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 3,
        "options": [
            "1,000,000 metric tons",
            "1:250,000 metric tons",
            "2,678,000 metric tons",
            "2,780,000 metric tons"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "geography",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 25,
        "year": 1998,
        "question": "What percentage of the world export commodities in figure 1 is represented by crude oil?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 3,
        "options": [
            "54.4%",
            "42.8%",
            "32.47%",
            "23.74%"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "geography",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 26,
        "year": 1998,
        "question": "In which of the following ways can the data shown in figure 1 be represented?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 1,
        "options": [
            "Simple bar graph",
            "Proprotional circle",
            "Dot map",
            "Chloropleth"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "geography",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 27,
        "year": 1998,
        "question": "Coal and mineral oil are usually found embedded in",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 3,
        "options": [
            "crystailline rocks",
            "igneous rocks",
            "metamorphic rocks",
            "sedimentary rocks"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    }
]